<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Buzzword Compliance]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-28T11:01:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jon Proulx]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cloudy Sysadmin Wanted]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2015/04/28/cloudy-sysadmin-wanted/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-28T09:59:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2015/04/28/cloudy-sysadmin-wanted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the down &amp; dirty, the position isn&rsquo;t posted yet and this is
the description our technical team has worked up so far and hasn&rsquo;t been
through the HR wringer yet.  But we want to fill this as
quickly as we can possibly find the right person so hoping this
informal post saves us a week or two while the bureaucracy churns.</p>

<p>The really really short version is we want someone who can help with
cloud ops and planning (<a href="http://www.openstack.org">OpenStack</a>,
<a href="http://ceph.com/">Ceph</a>, etc.) as well as direct random linux
support. Now at <a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu">CSAIL</a> we do support some
pretty amazing
<a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu/biographies/PI/biolist.php">people</a>, so that
part isn&rsquo;t all bad.</p>

<p>Once it&rsquo;s posted the wording may be a bit different but we&rsquo;ll still
be looking for more or less the same thing. Screening is pretty much
all technical staff so you don&rsquo;t need to tick off buzz words to get
through a pre screener that doesn&rsquo;t really understand what you&rsquo;re
talking about.</p>

<p>If you have question feel free to ask in the comments (or me privately
if you prefer).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested keep an eye on on <a href="http://careers.mit.edu/">http://careers.mit.edu/</a> (search for
Department &ldquo;Comp Sci &amp; Artificial Intelligence Lab&rdquo; and Employment
Type &ldquo;Full-Time&rdquo;).  There&rsquo;s only 6 listings today (without this one)
and none of them are even vaguely similar so should be obvious.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;ll <a href="https://twitter.com/_jon_proulx_">tweet</a> it. Hopefully
I&rsquo;ll edit this post as well and while it can&rsquo;t hurt to drop me an
email (jon at csail.mit.edu); I can&rsquo;t promise it will help either.</p>

<p>So the some what long winded description &hellip;</p>

<h2>Systems Administrator MIT/CSAIL</h2>

<p>Would you like to help provide the computing environment for one of
the premiere Computer Science research labs in the world?</p>

<p>The
<a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu">MIT Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory</a>
seeks a strong Linux generalist to join our
<a href="http://tig.csail.mit.edu">systems administration staff</a>.</p>

<p>The position is about half service development and server
operations and half customer support (generally as 2nd level to our
existing help desk). Roughly equivalent to a USNIX/LISA Level
III: Intermediate/Advanced System Administrator position.</p>

<h3>Required Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li><p> Strong interpersonal and communication skills; ability to write
 purchase justifications, train users in complex topics, make
 presentations to an internal audience, and interact positively
 with technical and non technical users</p></li>
<li><p> Independent problem-solving, self-direction</p></li>
<li><p> Comfort with most aspects of operating system administration; for
 example, managing processes and services, configuration of mail
 systems, system installation and configuration, printer systems,
 and fundamentals of security</p></li>
<li><p> Familiarity with the principles and practice of system
 configuration management using modern declarative tools; ability
 to model and reduce complex system requirements as configuration
 declarations</p></li>
<li><p> A solid understanding of the operating systems in use at the site
 (Ubuntu, Debian, FreeBSD, MacOS, Windows); understanding of
 paging and swapping, inter-process communication, devices and
 what device drivers do, and filesystem concepts, for this
 position Linux variants are most important</p></li>
<li><p> Familiarity with fundamental networking/distributed computing
 environment concepts; ability to configure file sharing
 (NFS/SAMBA or Windows); ability to query DNS records;
 understanding of basic routing concepts</p></li>
<li><p> Works well both independently and on a small team</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Required Background</h3>

<ul>
<li> Three to five years of system administration experience</li>
</ul>


<h3>Desirable Background and Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li><p> A degree in computer science or a related field</p></li>
<li><p> Ability to do minimal debugging and modification of C or Java
 programs</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Responsibilities</h3>

<ul>
<li><p> Receives general instructions for new responsibilities from supervisor</p></li>
<li><p> Initiates some new responsibilities and helps to plan for the
 future of the site</p></li>
<li><p> Mentor novice system administrators or operators</p></li>
<li><p> Receive mentoring from senior administrators</p></li>
<li><p> Evaluate and/or recommend purchases; has strong influence on
 purchasing process</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Current Technologies</h3>

<p>Roles often adapt to the person who fills them here, so we have a
certain expectation that the person we hire will not be doing exactly
the same set of things as the person who leaves. This is not an
absolute set of requirements so much as it is a wish list.</p>

<p>We try to stay at the forefront of emerging technologies.  Our
environment is constantly evolving and we value strong fundamental
understanding with a demonstrated ability to learn and adapt over
simply having a rote understanding of our current checklist of
applications and products.</p>

<h4>Core Systems (things your predecessor spent a lot of time on)</h4>

<ul>
<li> Ubuntu GNU/Linux</li>
<li> Puppet</li>
<li> Ceph</li>
<li> OpenStack</li>
<li> TiBS (backup software)</li>
<li> FAI (PXE based deployment)</li>
</ul>


<h4>Core Tools (things you&rsquo;ll need to use to get your job done)</h4>

<ul>
<li> Git</li>
<li> Request Tracker (RT)</li>
<li> Nagios</li>
</ul>


<h4>Languages</h4>

<ul>
<li><p>  Shell Scripting ability is a must</p></li>
<li><p> And at least one of Ruby or Python, bonus points for RAILS or
 Django knowledge.</p></li>
</ul>


<h4>Secondary (underlying technologies you&rsquo;ll frequently encounter in our environment)</h4>

<ul>
<li> Kerberos</li>
<li> OpenAFS</li>
<li> MySQL</li>
<li> Postgresql</li>
<li> Apache</li>
<li> NFS</li>
<li> ZFS</li>
<li> FreeBSD</li>
</ul>


<h4>Bonus (things you could optionally dive into)</h4>

<ul>
<li> HTCondor</li>
<li> ELK (or other logging/trending-fu)</li>
<li> Hadoop</li>
<li> Spark</li>
<li> AWS</li>
<li> Drupal</li>
<li> JunOS</li>
<li> MacOS</li>
<li> Windows</li>
</ul>


<h3>Hours and Location</h3>

<p>CSAIL is located in building 32 (the Stata Center) on MIT&rsquo;s Cambridge
Massachusetts campus.</p>

<p>As a new hire you will be expected to be on site 9-5. That said
once you&rsquo;ve come up to speed more flexibility to do remote
work is possible if you need some quieter time to focus on a project
or occasionally to deal with life&rsquo;s unexpected events (like contractors
or sick kids).</p>

<p>This position is part of an on call rotation.  On call duties are
shared between a primary and secondary responder for one week
shifts. Frequency fluctuates somewhat depending on staffing and
vacations, but typically in a six week period you&rsquo;ll be primary once
and secondary once.you will be on call once a month as either primary
or secondary responder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Don't Women Apply for Tech Jobs?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2014/10/19/why-dont-women-apply-for-tech-jobs/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-19T10:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2014/10/19/why-dont-women-apply-for-tech-jobs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This really is a question, so don&rsquo;t expect any answers from me, though
hopefully I can clarify (part) of the problem.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ve been thinking on for some time and
a <a href="https://twitter.com/bfcohen/status/523501000636641280">tweet</a> by Beth
Cohen (<a href="https://twitter.com/bfcohen">@bfcohen</a>) yesterday really caught my
attention, particularly:</p>

<blockquote><p><a href="http://dca.org.au/app/webroot/files/file/gender%20documents/Business%20Case%20for%20Women%20Mckinsey%20sept08.pdf">Research</a> shows that men apply for jobs for which they have 60% of the stated qualifications while women demur unless they have 100%.</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;ve fixated on that one point (of many) as I think it would have a
relatively large impact on getting women on a more even footing with
men for a relatively simple change. Like it or not advancement and
large salary changes in this industry are usually due to a job change
not just asking (much less not asking and relying on karma).</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Also confirmation bias.  I&rsquo;ve though as much for years, with a fair
level of certainty, but having a study to point to is nice.</p>

<h2>Women read job listings differently than men write them.</h2>

<p>In the nearly 15 years I&rsquo;ve been in my current job I can only think of
two female applicants who didn&rsquo;t get the job.  One was the
front runner until another woman who was even more qualified swooped
in and stole the show, the other actually just wasn&rsquo;t qualified.  I
can&rsquo;t even begin to count the number of unqualified male applicants
whose resumes have gone straight into the recycling&hellip;and yet we have
had and continue to have a preponderance of male employees.</p>

<p>The &lsquo;almost hired&rsquo; woman was someone I personally badgered into
applying because she was convinced after reading the job posting she
wasn&rsquo;t qualified because she didn&rsquo;t tick all the boxes on the
experience and qualification listed.  We never expected anyone would
(and no one did or really ever has).</p>

<p>Now it would have made a better story if she got the job, but the fact
is we don&rsquo;t hire just to put butts in seats here and if there had been
one fewer applicants in the pool she would have been hired. Clearly
applying was the right choice and there was a mismatch between her
expectations reading the job posing and our (all guy) expectation in
writing it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d suspected there was some gender miscommunication going on in the
way job posting were written and read prior to this, which is why I
even knew to try and talk her into applying.  That experience really
proved it pretty clearly to me.  A highly unscientific sampling of
women I knew at the time showed the same much more strict reading of
the job listing.</p>

<h2>So how do men write them?</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t <em>really</em> speak that broadly. Truth be told I&rsquo;m still in my
first technology job, a few promotions along perhaps. I&rsquo;ve interviewed
around enough to know that no one is expecting 100%.</p>

<p>A recruiter called me for one position with a clearly impossible set
of requirements and was explicitly told it was one description for two
positions and if I could fit &frac12; the requirements they&rsquo;d be
thrilled. Perhaps being that explicit in the written version would be
a start?</p>

<p>But I can only speak to the one hiring process I know from the inside,
so let&rsquo;s look at one job description as written. First though a BIG
caveat.  While this is a position as it was most recently posted, my
comments are my own and are not those of my employer or my coworkers
(in case you couldn&rsquo;t tell by the URL).</p>

<blockquote><p>JOB TITLE:         SRS Technical<br/>
POSITION TITLE:        System Administrator<br/>
DEPARTMENT:        XXXXX<br/>
DATE:          XXXXX</p></blockquote>

<p>OK that far is pretty neutral :) This is our entry level admin
position but is probably more mid-level from an industry perspective (I
think). Something between <a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/lisa/books/usenix_22_jobs3rd_core.pdf">SAGE levels</a> 2 &amp; 3.</p>

<blockquote><p>POSITION OVERVIEW STATEMENT</p>

<p>This System Administrator of the Infrastructure Group (TIG) in the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Lab (CSAIL) will be part of a small team responsible for configuring, troubleshooting, maintaining, and supporting systems for over 900 researchers, faculty, students, and staff, including Lab wide servers and services, servers belonging to research groups, and users&#8217; workstations and laptops. This work involves desktop operating systems including GNU/Linux, Mac OS, and Microsoft Windows, and server OSes including Debian, Ubuntu, and Windows, within a Kerberos/AFS environment. Will also mentor peers and interns, and participate in on-call rotation for off-hours and emergency support (requires carrying pager and cell phone).</p></blockquote>

<p>All of that is true as it describes the environment, but it&rsquo;s a catch
all.  Yes the person hired int this position would touch all those
things, eventually, but there&rsquo;s no expectation that the individual
would know &lsquo;GNU/Linux, Mac OS, and Microsoft Windows, and server OSes
including Debian, Ubuntu, and Windows&rsquo; much less Kerberos and AFS.</p>

<p>I look for a focused competence in one operating system and enough
knowledge of another to show some flexibility.  We have a chaotic
environment so people who just memorize the usual problems and their
usual solutions aren&rsquo;t going to work out very well.</p>

<blockquote><p>CHARACTERISTIC DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES (Essential Functions):</p>

<ul>
<li>Work with faculty, students, and staff in a technical support role, providing prompt responses through a web/email-based issue tracking system and in-person support.</li>
<li>Track all user support activity via a case-tracking system (RT), and monitor RT traffic for issues that need further follow-up or documentation as well as handling walk-up traffic user support issues.</li>
<li>Resolve client issues involving Microsoft Windows, Mac OS, Ubuntu and related applications (including but not limited to productivity software, IMAP email, web browsers and certificates, and other MIT accounting/HR software packages).</li>
<li>Rapidly diagnose and resolve faults with Lab-wide Debian, Ubuntu, and Windows servers and services (such as, but not limited to. Apache, SVN, Active Directory, mysql, DNS) and consulting with peers and communicating to users as appropriate</li>
<li>Take responsibility for maintaining and planning upgrades to various Lab-wide Debian, Ubuntu, and Windows servers, such as the Subversion server and Active Directory domain controllers.</li>
<li>Create and maintain installation instructions and other user-facing documentation, including creating customized installer packages</li>
<li>Install new and replacement workstations, laptops, and servers, including planning/staging, loading software and migrating data as necessary</li>
<li>Provide training in use of CSAIL and MIT computerized systems to new Lab members and experienced Lab members encountering new software and services.</li>
<li>Participate in on-call rotations for off-hours and emergency support (requires carrying SMS enabled cell phone)</li>
<li>Manage multiple tasks and issues simultaneously and communicate effectively and pleasantly with users and other TIG staff regarding problem resolution and the tracking issues.</li>
<li>Perform all related duties as assigned.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>This I probably didn&rsquo;t even read through when it was posted to hire
someone. Much of it is true, some seems like purely wishful thinking.</p>

<p>This was actually a mostly user facing position with server operations
and long term projects as a secondary function that was expected to be
largely learn as you go.</p>

<p>As such planning Active Directory server upgrades and rapidly
diagnosing Apache, SVN, MySQL, and DNS server issues is a bit of a
pipe dream.  In fact if someone were actually competent to do all that
I&rsquo;d probably judge them over qualified.  Any one of those skills would
get a star next to your name.</p>

<blockquote><p>SUPERVISION RECEIVED:  Reports to the Director of TIG; is responsible for determining work priorities and project follow up through completion.</p>

<p>SUPERVISION EXERCISED:  No direct supervisory responsibilities.</p>

<p>QUALIFICATIONS AND TECHNICAL SKILLS:
Bachelor&rsquo;s degree in computer science and 3 or more years of end-user support and system administration, preferably in an academic setting, or equivalent experience and training to include: an excellent working knowledge of GNU/Linux, MacOS, and Microsoft Windows operating systems both as an end-user and as an administrator and or in a Help Desk position. Requires excellent personal interaction skills, self-motivation and the ability to work through difficult problems with a minimal amount of support from senior staff members.   Requires a high degree of responsibility and punctuality. Demonstrated willingness and ability to pitch in wherever needed while still accomplishing primary goals.  Must have excellent oral and written communication, customer service, problem solving, analytical, and critical thinking skills; technical aptitude; reliability and ability to keep a consistent on-site schedule; ability to work independently to resolve client issues. Self-starter who is able to rapidly navigate a wide variety of technical problems and interpersonal interactions.  Requires carrying a cell phone to respond to off-hours emergencies.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is another wish list.  The apparently &ldquo;softer&rdquo; requirements like</p>

<blockquote><p>Requires excellent personal interaction skills, self-motivation and
the ability to work through difficult problems with a minimal amount
of support from senior staff members</p></blockquote>

<p>are actually the more important.  Any specifics mentioned are an ideal
list to provide a measure of candidates and like all rulers it need
to be a bit longer than anything we&rsquo;re likely to measure.</p>

<p>The degree requirement is bull shit, I&rsquo;d much rather &lsquo;equivalent
experience&rsquo;.  They don&rsquo;t teach systems administration anywhere I&rsquo;ve
seen, when hiring developers a bit of formal CS probably has more meaning.
For this position I&rsquo;d be surprised if you didn&rsquo;t finish High School
but it wouldn&rsquo;t be an immediate disqualifier to me.</p>

<h2>Wow that&rsquo;s kinda crap isn&rsquo;t it?</h2>

<p>Well yes.</p>

<p>I suspect some of it is sloppy copy-pasta as we recycle these things
and tweak them a bit depending on the job focus and level.  But a bit
of it shows we&rsquo;re playing to another audience as well.</p>

<p>This job description also goes to HR and we need to convince them to
pay something that&rsquo;s not too insulting.  Some of the secret code words
are in there for them (like the Bachelor&rsquo;s degree in CS).</p>

<p>Clearly even gender politics a side there&rsquo;s quite a bit that could be
better here, but that is how things go out.  Looking around I don&rsquo;t
think my group are the only sloppy people out there.  So what is to be
done?</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s not your job to eliminate yourself.</h2>

<p>I think the wisest thing that was ever said to me in relation to job
applications is that &ldquo;it isn&rsquo;t your job to eliminate yourself&rdquo;.  I&rsquo;d
pass the same advice along to any job seeker.</p>

<p>Present yourself honestly, but apply boldly.  If the position seems
interesting and you have 50% or better of the qualifications listed go
for it!  These days you don&rsquo;t even waste a stamp.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re nervous about doing that, start with positions you don&rsquo;t
care about.  Maybe you&rsquo;ll even get to turn some down, which is great
for the ego I hear.</p>

<h2>What about better job descriptions?</h2>

<p>Well that&rsquo;s the issue, I don&rsquo;t know.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have a list of hard requirement since we have a loose and
adaptive &ldquo;structure&rdquo; here.  We need to cover this broad area and have
N positions to do so.  When a position is open it&rsquo;s usually because
someone has left.</p>

<p>Obviously they have a specific skill set that the group has adapted to
and usually the ideal person to fill it would be a clone of them.
This person never exists so we cast a broader net, and plan that where
the new hire&rsquo;s skills don&rsquo;t match the vacant position we can adjust
the focus of other team members so we still have full or near full
coverage, then train up any remaining gaps.</p>

<p>This doesn&rsquo;t lend itself to a truly clear list of &lsquo;these are the
essential skills&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Also to be realistic any job description is going to be used over
multiple jobs each with a slightly different focus and laziness will
keep us recycling the same description without making fine adjustments
to the relative importance of different qualifications.</p>

<p>Perhaps some thing as simple as stating &ldquo;While an ideal candidate would
have these skills, the successful candidate should have at least 75%
of them&rdquo; as mentioned above?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve heard from women in the industry that describing the position
rather than a long list of skills would be an improvement.  This
description actually tried to move in that direction. I don&rsquo;t
think it was very successful in that.  There&rsquo;s no bullet list
labeled &lsquo;required skills&rsquo; but it still rather reads like it is.  Also
the Overview and Characteristic Duties section covers about 2/3 of the
the &lsquo;small team&rsquo; and there&rsquo;s no indication that the applicant and
several other people divide up those responsibilities.</p>

<p>Now if you get in for an interview we do tend to be more explicit with
how responsibilities are divided and which of them we&rsquo;re currently
most interested in.  To get an interview we first need to get an
application though.</p>

<p>While I don&rsquo;t have any open positions now, and hopefully won&rsquo;t for some
time, it would be awfully nice to be ready with a job description that
would reach a larger more diverse audience.  As it is we have a hell
of a time getting decent candidates s,o justice and equity aside,
anything that reaches a larger number of qualified candidates would
be a bit win.</p>

<p>This probably isn&rsquo;t even strictly a gender issue, though that&rsquo;s the
context I&rsquo;ve heard about it most in.  It may well be much more broadly
exclusionary. Really when I originally applied to a similar
advertisement many years ago (so long ago I think it did cost me a
stamp) I only did it because I was desperate and was certain I
wouldn&rsquo;t hear back, yet here I am.</p>

<p>Anyone have a sysadmin job description written to try and address this
issue?  What would be really great is to hear from some women in
the field what advertisement for their job looked like and how they
would write an ad for it.</p>

<p>Discuss, please&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Should It Be Easy to Install OpenStack?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2014/10/12/openstack-install/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-12T11:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2014/10/12/openstack-install</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of my glorious position on the
<a href="http://www.openstack.org/foundation/user-committee">OpensStack User Committee</a>
(note to self submit bio for user committee page) I recently went
through all 619 free response comments collected by the
<a href="https://www.openstack.org/user-survey">user survey</a> in the past 12
months.  The point of that exercise was to come up with a very coarse
&ldquo;Top 10&rdquo; list to be presented with the tabulated survey results in
<a href="https://www.openstack.org/summit/openstack-paris-summit-2014/">Paris</a>.</p>

<p>One of the things that kept coming up (though in the end finished out
of the money so no spoilers here) was making it easier to install
OpenStack.  Certainly this is an area though could use improvement,
but how much can it be improved and is it even OpenStack&rsquo;s business to
worry about installers?</p>

<p>When wearing my &lsquo;user committee&rsquo; hat I had to be neutral and try and
interpret the anonymous responses I was looking at as faithfully as
possible without any editorializing.  Well I&rsquo;m takin that hat off now
and putting on my more usual &lsquo;grumpy old bastard&rsquo; hat, so hold on kids
it&rsquo;s going to be a bumpy ride&hellip;</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>You will never get a unicorn.</h2>

<p>Your package manager cannot help you here, <code>apt-get install openstack</code>
will never do what you want (nor will <code>yum install</code> or <code>emerge</code> or any
of the other variants Linux or otherwise).  There are simply too many
pieces and too many choices for this to ever really be practical, so
just get that idea out of your silly little head.</p>

<p>One of OpenStack&rsquo;s strength is it&rsquo;s flexibility and modularity. I&rsquo;m of
the opinion that this is the main reason it is currently dominant in
the private cloud space while more monolithic projects (ahem
<a href="https://www.eucalyptus.com/">Eucalyptus</a>) have all but faded
away. It&rsquo;s certainly why I threw away my Eucalyptus based cloud about
2 years ago, but I digress.</p>

<p>Flexibility necessarily brings some complexity. Now I think choice is
good, but perhaps you think things have gotten a bit out of
hand. Perhaps we have gone too far in the trade off between
flexibility and simplicity, but even if we could put that genie back
in the bottle divide the available options by 10 and you&rsquo;d still be
there all day long answering preinstall questions.</p>

<p>The main problem isn&rsquo;t even the millions of config options it&rsquo;s how
the setting those option affects what packages you need to install in
the first place. Which services will you provide? Keystone, Nova, and
Glance are pretty much required for an IaaS install (we&rsquo;ll assume a
different meta-package for a storage focused install what wouldn&rsquo;t
need those), but what about Cinder and if Cinder what storage backend?
Even with the most minimal (and somewhat unrealistic) IaaS
requirements, what hypervisor will you use, what storage will you use
for Glance these both have a big impact on what packages you
need. We&rsquo;ll wave hands over the Neutron options because those are just
crazy, but you do need to consider which RPC backend to use and I&rsquo;d
really like to see a choice of database backend as well.</p>

<p>&ldquo;But choice doesn&rsquo;t mean we can&rsquo;t have reasonable defaults&rdquo;, you say?
OK that&rsquo;s true. Suppose there&rsquo;s a magic package that makes all theses
choices and leave it to you to install by pieces if you want to make
different choices.</p>

<p>Well that unicorn isn&rsquo;t shooting rainbows out it&rsquo;s ass anymore, but
still a unicorn I&rsquo;ll grant. Here&rsquo;s the final kicker, OpenStack is
fundamentally a distributed system that can be decomposed in multiple
ways. Single controller, separate controller and network node are the
two most popular will there be separate Cinder nodes or will that be on
the controller?</p>

<p>Now maybe we can assume more defaults to simplify this, like a single
non HA controller that will do everything and we can add compute nodes
to talk to later. Well that isn&rsquo;t a unicorn anymore it&rsquo;s a toy. I&rsquo;ve
got nothing against playing with toys, they are useful for simple
testing and experimental learning.  If that&rsquo;s what you&rsquo;re looking for
you probably want a pony, I&rsquo;ll talk about those later.</p>

<h2>But I saw one over there.</h2>

<p>&ldquo;That last argument was a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man">straw man</a> there are plenty of
ways to get my unicorn that don&rsquo;t rely on anything as crude as package
managers.&rdquo; Well that&rsquo;s true there are better ways to try and get your
unicorn, but I didn&rsquo;t make up that argument.  Someone actually wanted
to avoid &lsquo;kludging&rsquo; around with configuration management systems.</p>

<p>So yes can get better install automation by leveraging the
configuration management system of your choice.  In fact you&rsquo;re
a bit mad if you don&rsquo;t, but this is not a unicorn either it&rsquo;s just good
sense and takes a deep understanding of OpenStack to configure properly.
Perhaps less so than just installing raw as you can play a bit of
&ldquo;fill in the blanks&rdquo; to get things going, but still somewhat less than
magical.</p>

<p><a href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO">TripleO</a>? Yes, fine that may
be magical.  The OpenStack on OpenStack, OpenStack as a Service,
infinitely recursive, inceptiony thing may in fact have enough mojo to
do this in its perfected state. I haven&rsquo;t been following just how
close its current state is to this, but I will grant that it may grow
up to be a unicorn if it isn&rsquo;t already.</p>

<h2>You don&rsquo;t <em>really</em> want a unicorn anyway.</h2>

<p>Well not at first.</p>

<p>OpenStack in production is probably going to be a fairly important
part of your infrastructure. What is the point of a cloud if not to run
many more systems on the cloud than under it?</p>

<p>For something with your whole computational world riding on it, you
NEED to understand what the pieces are and how they are put together
in a very deliberate way. When something goes wrong you need to be
able to understand what is happening.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never met a piece of software that hasn&rsquo;t broken on me at some
point in some way. Software (and hardware for that matter) that is in
the critical path demands either a commercial support contract with a
very short response time or equivalent local expertise. Of course, being
local expertise, I prefer the latter there are plenty of people in the
ecosystem who will sell you the former as well.</p>

<p>Unicorns get you neither of these things.  If there were a silver
bullet, answer three questions and have a working OpenStack installer,
what would you do when something went wrong at 3am on a Saturday?</p>

<h2>Perhaps a pony then?</h2>

<p>Yes a pony would be nice.</p>

<h3>Toys for learning</h3>

<p>Being able to quickly setup a working OpenStack environment to
evaluate if it is worth looking into more deeply, is an entirely
reasonable goal.  As is getting a running cloud so you can learn how
it behaves through observing and deconstructing it.  Both of these are
a long way from production and can be expected to be done with little
to no OpenStack experience.</p>

<p>I used <a href="http://fai-project.org/">FAI</a>, which we use for PXE bast boot
strapping around here, and <a href="http://puppetlabs.com/">Puppet</a>to do the
actual OpenStack config bits for my first install (after an abortive
attempt at using <a href="https://maas.ubuntu.com/">MaaS</a> which conflicted
with too many existing services on my network).  Had a working multi
node proof of concept system up in less than 16 person hours from
deciding to hunt up abandoned hardware to having test users launching
VMs. Granted this was during the Essex release so pre-Neutron,
somewhat simpler times.</p>

<p>Today the official <a href="http://docs.openstack.org/">install guides</a> would
probably be both faster and better, since you can see the individual
pieces fitting together as you assemble them rather than first taking
a magical leap and then having to deconstruct what it did as it the
case with Puppet (or your tool of choice most likely).</p>

<p>Both these methods are a bit more time investment than one would
really want for the initial
evaluation. <a href="http://devstack.org/">DevStack</a> will get something
quickly with out too much investment, but as a developer tool it&rsquo;s not
quite an ideal operator evaluation tool. An introductory level unicorn
would be a good creature to have, so long as people understand it&rsquo;s
mythical nature and don&rsquo;t try to ride it all the way into production.</p>

<h3>Making a plan</h3>

<p>Even a pony can&rsquo;t help you here.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve come to understand the basics of how OpenStack is put
together in the basic sense from the above {de,re}construction, it&rsquo;s
time to find the union of what you want with what you can have an hope
that it includes what you need (it probably will).</p>

<p>The only way to do this is to do it. Iterate through configs either by
hand or preferably through your config engine until you get what you
want.</p>

<p>Only <a href="http://docs.openstack.org/">Docs</a> can help you here.  Now the
docs team works amazing hours and does great work, but keeping up
with the pace of OpenStack is near impossible.  If you find something
confusing, outdated, or just plain wrong there&rsquo;s a little red bug icon
on the top right of every page, click that and report it.</p>

<p>Ultimately in our perfectly documented world this iteration is still
necessary if only to prove the behavior described is actually what
you want.</p>

<h3>Executing the plan</h3>

<p>Once the hard design work is done you just feed that into your
existing configuration management system like you&rsquo;ve been doing for
all you server configs for years right?</p>

<p>Pretty much yes. Different tool communities have different bumps in
their particular processes, but if you pick the devil that you know
you can pretty much anticipate what those are</p>

<h2>So how is this OpenStack&rsquo;s business.</h2>

<p>Well in my opinion it&rsquo;s not really.</p>

<p>In a broad sense reducing over all complexity to the extent we can
and choosing reasonable defaults so fewer of the myriad config options
need to be set are good goals that are in scope and would help
simplify installs, but that&rsquo;s really a side effect, simplifying on
going management is the main need for those. You install infrequently
(maybe once) but systems management is forever.</p>

<p>Packaging is your distro&rsquo;s business which is as it should be, for
example when have you ever tried to install <a href="http://www.x.org">X</a> from
upstream or install
<a href="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/">Linux From Scratch</a>? These are
instructive experiences but you probably wouldn&rsquo;t base you
infrastructure on do that. Of course if you are deploying from trunk
then you don&rsquo;t need packages, but you do need a CI/CD team and have
more complex problems than any dreamed of here.</p>

<p>Configuration management is the union of the OpenStack and tool
communities. You&rsquo;ll see sessions for various tools at
<a href="https://www.openstack.org/summit">Summits</a>, midcycle OPS meetups, and
on <a href="https://github.com/stackforg">StackForge</a>, but they are not
properly OpenStack projects.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;re of course free to disagree, and build a native magical
installer if you want.  As I said choice is good. But if you&rsquo;re going
to hate on how hard OpenStack is to install try and remember what it
was like to install a GNU/Linux operating system when it was four
years old (say 1997 when the <a href="http://www.debian.org">Debian</a> disto
was 4). OpenStack is a dream compared to that, so quit whining and get
to <a href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/How_To_Contribute">work</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
