<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Openstack | Buzzword Compliance]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/categories/openstack/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-27T08:07:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jon Proulx]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenStack's Opportunity for Disruption]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2015/10/27/openstacks-opportunity-for-disruption/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-27T06:49:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2015/10/27/openstacks-opportunity-for-disruption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenStack has a huge opportunity to truly disrupt the cloud space but
I&rsquo;m afraid no one is noticing this.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Cloud is more confining than you think</h2>

<p>&ldquo;Cloud&rdquo; is still though of by many as a disruptive and freeing model.
In fact it&rsquo;s old news and has become some what ossified.  There&rsquo;s
innovation on top but not really in what cloud fundamentally are.</p>

<p>All clouds are run by a single provider (which may be yourself in the
case of private clouds), but that provider fully defines the cloud
environment, what services are available and what hardware those
services run on.  In the simplest IaaS case you get something like this.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/assets/everycloud.png" width="389" height="264"></p>

<p>Now we can add more services like object storage, orchestration,
image management, and compose lower level services into
Fubar-as-a-Service.  But everything must live within that cloud
boundary.</p>

<p>This boundary issue is common to all clouds I&rsquo;m aware of.</p>

<p>In OpenStack land we do a lot of work on interoperability and
federation between clouds.  This allows you to (more) easily migrate
workloads from one OpenStack cloud to another.  This is all well and
good but the explosion in containers really ate our lunch
there. There&rsquo;s still lots of value to federation and defcore, but
neither will change the world if you want portable workloads
containerize.</p>

<p>Still, moving workloads is one thing but each is still islanded in
what ever cloud they are launched on and can only draw resources from
that pool.  The fluffy cloud is really more of a prison cell, even if
it maybe a minimum security one.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/assets/jailcloud.png" width="301" height="312"></p>

<p>No one much notices because that&rsquo;s the way it has always been.  You
pick your cloud or clouds and live in them.</p>

<h2>Multi-Provider Cloud</h2>

<p>Multi-provider cloud could change everything and it&rsquo;s <em>almost</em>
possible with existing OpenStack using federation.  We just need to
break the internal assumptions that there can be only one of each
service.</p>

<p>There was a cross project working session this afternoon at the Tokyo
OpenStack Summit to address this and a working demo on a Nova instance
in one cloud attaching a Cinder volume in another cloud.</p>

<p>This is revolutionary.</p>

<p>This reshapes the cloud marketplace.  Rather than competing with full
cloud stacks vendors could specialize in what they actually do
well. Users could select the best components for their needs rather
than the best compromise.  Hybrid clouds could burst out and get some
compute from a public provider while still utilizing their private
image and block storage services.</p>

<p>We can see the sun through the clouds!</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/assets/ocx.png" width="347" height="245"></p>

<p>No one showed up.</p>

<p>OK that&rsquo;s not true.  A number of operators showed up that I
recognized,.  And lots of Keystone people showed up, but they were
mostly already on board.  What was missing was, well everyone else and
if this is to happen it will likely need everyone else.</p>

<p>I was a bit disappointed by that.</p>

<h2>Massachussetts Open Cloud</h2>

<p>This work is being done largely by
<a href="http://www.massopenclooud.org">Mass Open Cloud</a> you can find some older
presentations and papers there.</p>

<p>Also like all OpenStack shops they&rsquo;re hiring (dev and ops)&hellip;</p>

<p>I recently hitched my wagon to them (my waggon bein gMIT/CSAIL&rsquo;s
production cloud) since we were building clouds in the same
data-center we decided to combine efforts. I do production ops things
so while I&rsquo;m working with them that part of the project isn&rsquo;t my baby.
Though my interest in seeing it happen is a large part of why I
decided to partner with them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
