<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Career, | Buzzword Compliance]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/categories/career/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-28T11:01:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jon Proulx]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cloudy Sysadmin Wanted]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2015/04/28/cloudy-sysadmin-wanted/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-28T09:59:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.iwokeupcoveredinblood.com/blog/2015/04/28/cloudy-sysadmin-wanted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the down &amp; dirty, the position isn&rsquo;t posted yet and this is
the description our technical team has worked up so far and hasn&rsquo;t been
through the HR wringer yet.  But we want to fill this as
quickly as we can possibly find the right person so hoping this
informal post saves us a week or two while the bureaucracy churns.</p>

<p>The really really short version is we want someone who can help with
cloud ops and planning (<a href="http://www.openstack.org">OpenStack</a>,
<a href="http://ceph.com/">Ceph</a>, etc.) as well as direct random linux
support. Now at <a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu">CSAIL</a> we do support some
pretty amazing
<a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu/biographies/PI/biolist.php">people</a>, so that
part isn&rsquo;t all bad.</p>

<p>Once it&rsquo;s posted the wording may be a bit different but we&rsquo;ll still
be looking for more or less the same thing. Screening is pretty much
all technical staff so you don&rsquo;t need to tick off buzz words to get
through a pre screener that doesn&rsquo;t really understand what you&rsquo;re
talking about.</p>

<p>If you have question feel free to ask in the comments (or me privately
if you prefer).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested keep an eye on on <a href="http://careers.mit.edu/">http://careers.mit.edu/</a> (search for
Department &ldquo;Comp Sci &amp; Artificial Intelligence Lab&rdquo; and Employment
Type &ldquo;Full-Time&rdquo;).  There&rsquo;s only 6 listings today (without this one)
and none of them are even vaguely similar so should be obvious.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;ll <a href="https://twitter.com/_jon_proulx_">tweet</a> it. Hopefully
I&rsquo;ll edit this post as well and while it can&rsquo;t hurt to drop me an
email (jon at csail.mit.edu); I can&rsquo;t promise it will help either.</p>

<p>So the some what long winded description &hellip;</p>

<h2>Systems Administrator MIT/CSAIL</h2>

<p>Would you like to help provide the computing environment for one of
the premiere Computer Science research labs in the world?</p>

<p>The
<a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu">MIT Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory</a>
seeks a strong Linux generalist to join our
<a href="http://tig.csail.mit.edu">systems administration staff</a>.</p>

<p>The position is about half service development and server
operations and half customer support (generally as 2nd level to our
existing help desk). Roughly equivalent to a USNIX/LISA Level
III: Intermediate/Advanced System Administrator position.</p>

<h3>Required Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li><p> Strong interpersonal and communication skills; ability to write
 purchase justifications, train users in complex topics, make
 presentations to an internal audience, and interact positively
 with technical and non technical users</p></li>
<li><p> Independent problem-solving, self-direction</p></li>
<li><p> Comfort with most aspects of operating system administration; for
 example, managing processes and services, configuration of mail
 systems, system installation and configuration, printer systems,
 and fundamentals of security</p></li>
<li><p> Familiarity with the principles and practice of system
 configuration management using modern declarative tools; ability
 to model and reduce complex system requirements as configuration
 declarations</p></li>
<li><p> A solid understanding of the operating systems in use at the site
 (Ubuntu, Debian, FreeBSD, MacOS, Windows); understanding of
 paging and swapping, inter-process communication, devices and
 what device drivers do, and filesystem concepts, for this
 position Linux variants are most important</p></li>
<li><p> Familiarity with fundamental networking/distributed computing
 environment concepts; ability to configure file sharing
 (NFS/SAMBA or Windows); ability to query DNS records;
 understanding of basic routing concepts</p></li>
<li><p> Works well both independently and on a small team</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Required Background</h3>

<ul>
<li> Three to five years of system administration experience</li>
</ul>


<h3>Desirable Background and Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li><p> A degree in computer science or a related field</p></li>
<li><p> Ability to do minimal debugging and modification of C or Java
 programs</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Responsibilities</h3>

<ul>
<li><p> Receives general instructions for new responsibilities from supervisor</p></li>
<li><p> Initiates some new responsibilities and helps to plan for the
 future of the site</p></li>
<li><p> Mentor novice system administrators or operators</p></li>
<li><p> Receive mentoring from senior administrators</p></li>
<li><p> Evaluate and/or recommend purchases; has strong influence on
 purchasing process</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Current Technologies</h3>

<p>Roles often adapt to the person who fills them here, so we have a
certain expectation that the person we hire will not be doing exactly
the same set of things as the person who leaves. This is not an
absolute set of requirements so much as it is a wish list.</p>

<p>We try to stay at the forefront of emerging technologies.  Our
environment is constantly evolving and we value strong fundamental
understanding with a demonstrated ability to learn and adapt over
simply having a rote understanding of our current checklist of
applications and products.</p>

<h4>Core Systems (things your predecessor spent a lot of time on)</h4>

<ul>
<li> Ubuntu GNU/Linux</li>
<li> Puppet</li>
<li> Ceph</li>
<li> OpenStack</li>
<li> TiBS (backup software)</li>
<li> FAI (PXE based deployment)</li>
</ul>


<h4>Core Tools (things you&rsquo;ll need to use to get your job done)</h4>

<ul>
<li> Git</li>
<li> Request Tracker (RT)</li>
<li> Nagios</li>
</ul>


<h4>Languages</h4>

<ul>
<li><p>  Shell Scripting ability is a must</p></li>
<li><p> And at least one of Ruby or Python, bonus points for RAILS or
 Django knowledge.</p></li>
</ul>


<h4>Secondary (underlying technologies you&rsquo;ll frequently encounter in our environment)</h4>

<ul>
<li> Kerberos</li>
<li> OpenAFS</li>
<li> MySQL</li>
<li> Postgresql</li>
<li> Apache</li>
<li> NFS</li>
<li> ZFS</li>
<li> FreeBSD</li>
</ul>


<h4>Bonus (things you could optionally dive into)</h4>

<ul>
<li> HTCondor</li>
<li> ELK (or other logging/trending-fu)</li>
<li> Hadoop</li>
<li> Spark</li>
<li> AWS</li>
<li> Drupal</li>
<li> JunOS</li>
<li> MacOS</li>
<li> Windows</li>
</ul>


<h3>Hours and Location</h3>

<p>CSAIL is located in building 32 (the Stata Center) on MIT&rsquo;s Cambridge
Massachusetts campus.</p>

<p>As a new hire you will be expected to be on site 9-5. That said
once you&rsquo;ve come up to speed more flexibility to do remote
work is possible if you need some quieter time to focus on a project
or occasionally to deal with life&rsquo;s unexpected events (like contractors
or sick kids).</p>

<p>This position is part of an on call rotation.  On call duties are
shared between a primary and secondary responder for one week
shifts. Frequency fluctuates somewhat depending on staffing and
vacations, but typically in a six week period you&rsquo;ll be primary once
and secondary once.you will be on call once a month as either primary
or secondary responder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
